<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>travel on Bryan Shalloway&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/travel/</link>
    <description>Recent content in travel on Bryan Shalloway&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/travel/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Iceland Day 6: Perlan &amp; Departure</title>
      <link>/2020/01/01/iceland-day-6-perlan-departure/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/01/iceland-day-6-perlan-departure/</guid>
      <description>I did my best to convince Britney and my parents that we should start the morning with a ‘polar bear plunge’ in the ocean but was unsuccessful in convincing anyone (including myself) to participate. We slept in and had a relaxing morning before leaving the Airbnb at around 12PM.
We headed to the Perlan, where we’d had dinner a few nights prior and which also served as the city’s science center1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Iceland Day 5: Blue Lagoon &amp; New Year’s Eve</title>
      <link>/2019/12/31/iceland-day-5-blue-lagoon-new-year-s-eve/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/31/iceland-day-5-blue-lagoon-new-year-s-eve/</guid>
      <description>We were out the door by 7:45AM and headed for the Blue Lagoon (where my parents had offered to treat us for the day). The regular Blue Lagoon pool had sold-out of tickets. Instead, we were ‘forced’ to get tickets to the Blue Lagoon Spa Retreat – setting the stage for the most luxurious four hours of my life.
Changing room in the Blue Lagoon Spa Retreat
In addition to access to the main lagoon, the retreat included four secluded winding pools that were perfect for laying back and slowly floating down.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Iceland Day 4: Southeast Coast &amp; Diamond Beach</title>
      <link>/2019/12/30/iceland-day-4-southeast-coast-diamond-beach/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/30/iceland-day-4-southeast-coast-diamond-beach/</guid>
      <description>Britney and I awoke several times in the night to the frigid cold. We would run across the street to a patch of trees where we could relieve ourselves and get away from the streetlights. I looked up to the stars and the clear night sky clinging faintly to a hope that whatever damage might be done to the car, it was all part of a plan for us to be at this exact point.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Iceland Day 3: Thingvellier &amp; Disaster</title>
      <link>/2019/12/29/iceland-day-3-thingvellier-disaster/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/29/iceland-day-3-thingvellier-disaster/</guid>
      <description>We slept in a little later this morning (930AM), had Skyr parfaits with mom and dad for breakfast and more croissants from Brauð &amp;amp; Co. We drove back to the UNESCO World heritage site, Thingvellier, that we’d attempted to visit the morning before. We arrived close to sunrise (there was no creepy white pickup truck in the parking lot this time).
The drive out was beautiful and easy. The browning grass and gnarled branches by the road seemed almost a pastoral desert (except for all the wetness).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Iceland Day 2: Golden Circle &amp; Snowmobiling</title>
      <link>/2019/12/28/iceland-day-2-golden-circle-snowmobiling/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/28/iceland-day-2-golden-circle-snowmobiling/</guid>
      <description>I grabbed an assortment of croissants from Brauð &amp;amp; Co, half a block from our apartment. We were on the road headed East by 7:05AM.
The morning was strikingly dark. Clouds obscured any starlight. A soft rain made everything reflective. Faint glimpses of small trees and twisted wooden branches looked like alien figures on the side of the road. I drove nervously, stooping over the wheel like my dad had the morning before.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Iceland Day 1: Landing &amp; City Tour</title>
      <link>/2019/12/27/iceland-day-1-landing-city-tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/27/iceland-day-1-landing-city-tour/</guid>
      <description>My parents, Britney and I landed in Reykjavik at 630AM. We’d taken an eight-and-a-half-hour overnight flight from Seattle. It was dark when we stepped off the plane and would remain dark until 11AM (in wintertime Iceland only gets 4-6 hours of sunlight a day).
I packed the bags into haphazard piles that poured over the rear storage area of our rented Nissan X-trail. The air was a cold mix of rain and mist.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>