<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>travel on Bryan Shalloway&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/travel/</link>
    <description>Recent content in travel on Bryan Shalloway&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/travel/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Iceland Day 6: Perlan &amp; Departure</title>
      <link>/2020/01/01/iceland-day-6-perlan-departure/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/01/iceland-day-6-perlan-departure/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;I did my best to convince Britney and my parents that we should start the morning with a ‘polar bear plunge’ in the ocean but was unsuccessful in convincing anyone (including myself) to participate. We slept in and had a relaxing morning before leaving the Airbnb at around 12PM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We headed to the Perlan, where we’d had dinner a few nights prior and which also served as the city’s science center&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. We watched an aurora show in the planetarium, trekked through an artificial glacial ice cave&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, walked around the city observation deck and perused various exhibits that showcased information on Icelandic geology and local flora and fauna. I fiercely negotiated with dad to let us stay as late as possible (our flight was at 5PM).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/U7aHuTI.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Before the show started, the planetarium gave everyone a chance to flash selfies with the auroral backdrop overhead&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Before the show started, the planetarium gave everyone a chance to flash selfies with the auroral backdrop overhead&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/YcrIT62.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Ice throne in the ice cave&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Ice throne in the ice cave&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/zUDm4Bc.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Climbing the interior sides of an artificial ice cave&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Climbing the interior sides of an artificial ice cave&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After seeing the exhibits we raced back to the city center so that I could get one of the famous Icelandic hot dogs from Baejarins Beztu Pylsur&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Dad was tense while driving – he likes to get to the airport several hours before his flight. Once I had a full belly I was able to stop teasing him about his “obsession with the airport lounge” and we eventually stopped trying to press each other’s buttons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was light outside. I enjoyed gazing at the volcanic wasteland by the airport (something we couldn’t see in the darkness of our arrival flight). As our departure approached a vaporous haze slowly filled the air. The volcanic scenes faded into a misty canvased backdrop on which I played out memories from the week. When the airplane took-off it was too foggy to catch a final glimpse of the city, or to give a farewell – I guess we will have to come back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Britney packed-up the car this time (rather than me), so we were no longer threatened by our bags tumbling all over us at any bump or sharp turn.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a result of the misadventures on Day 3, we’d had to miss an ice cave hike we’d planned, so the Perlan’s artificial ice cave provided a conciliation.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was near the Parliament building where our tour on day one had started.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Iceland Day 5: Blue Lagoon &amp; New Year’s Eve</title>
      <link>/2019/12/31/iceland-day-5-blue-lagoon-new-year-s-eve/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/31/iceland-day-5-blue-lagoon-new-year-s-eve/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;We were out the door by 7:45AM and headed for the Blue Lagoon (where my parents had offered to treat us for the day). The regular Blue Lagoon pool had sold-out of tickets. Instead, we were ‘forced’ to get tickets to the Blue Lagoon &lt;em&gt;Spa Retreat&lt;/em&gt; – setting the stage for the most luxurious four hours of my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/KYJLPDA.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Changing room in the Blue Lagoon Spa Retreat&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Changing room in the Blue Lagoon Spa Retreat&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to access to the main lagoon, the retreat included four secluded winding pools that were perfect for laying back and slowly floating down. Everything was open and empty, it felt as though you were laying back in the mouth of your own personal volcano. There were also saunas, steam rooms, self-service salt scrubs, fire pits, even an on-demand photographer for goodness sake!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/Nz7NQQq.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Part of the winding pools in the Blue Lagoon Spa Retreat&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Part of the winding pools in the Blue Lagoon Spa Retreat&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My parents also gave Britney and I their water massages because they said they simply “Wanted to spend the whole time together.” This may sound cute but was &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; just bad decision making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The water massage starts when “Chad” – muscle bound in a tight black nylon tank-top – invites you to lay onto a foam bed floating on the water. At first you may feel up-tight, but in his powerful arms and instructions to “make your limbs like wet spaghetti” you surrender yourself. Chad covers you with a warm water-soaked blanket and then cradles you while massaging every part. Floating there and safe in his arms you will never get so close to returning to the womb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We spent ~4 hours at the blue lagoon, drinking, eating, soaking, and &lt;em&gt;relaxing.&lt;/em&gt; When we got back to the Airbnb, Britney laid back for a nap and fell asleep with a slight upturned smile that was a picture of serenity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/p5Px2tU.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Leaving the Blue Lagoon&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Leaving the Blue Lagoon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took this time to continue my wanderings through Reykjavik. I stopped for some local Rhubarb flavored ice cream&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, then picked-up black volcanic table salt for my parents&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and mushroom hot cocoa mix for Britney&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I stepped into a clothing store (that was in view of the Christmas Cat) and purchased a locally woven wool scarf-blanket on behalf of my mom (which she gave to Britney to serve as a warm memento of the trip). I continued on my way, stopping at important sites across the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/nitD2KY.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The “Voyager” statue behind me commemorates the Viking explorers and freedom&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The “Voyager” statue behind me commemorates the Viking explorers and freedom&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before returning to the apartment I went by the Hallgrimskirkja church courtyard and scoped out ideal spots for fireworks viewing. Iceland’s New Year’s celebration features one of the most impressive fireworks displays in all the world. Each resident spends several paychecks on fireworks (the selling of which is used to raise funds for public services) which are then set-off with increasing frequency leading up to midnight&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For dinner, dad, Britney, and I went down to an Italian place on Reykjavik harbor named Caruso&lt;a href=&#34;#fn5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Dad and Britney ordered pasta while I ate lamb. Once again, everything was delicious. Dad told stories about the history of lean-agile software development; I mostly looked out the window and enjoyed the water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We drove back to the Airbnb and laid on the bed for a few minutes. Britney and I were starting to feel worn down&lt;a href=&#34;#fn6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. We eventually assembled ourselves and headed for the outskirts of Reykjavik to attend a traditional New Year’s bonfire event&lt;a href=&#34;#fn7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref7&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could see the fire at a distance from our approach; the flaming orange stack stood over two stories high. Britney had me give her a piggyback ride across the wet grass; I sloshed us over to the encirclement. We arrived just as the locals were singing a final Icelandic song and throwing the last few planks of wood onto the blaze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/B3RhKj5.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;New Year’s Eve bonfire at Geirsnef park&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;New Year’s Eve bonfire at Geirsnef park&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sounds of the crackling wood were mixed in with amicable banter between us and a German couple with whom we compared itineraries. The park gave an expansive view of the city, which was starting to come alive with fireworks. Flashes in the distance left sparkling plumes that alighted over the massive conflagration before us. I sipped a poorly concocted mushroom cocoa &amp;amp; coconut vodka mix from a thermos and basked in the heat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I asked a local if there was any hidden meaning in the bonfire. I posited (paraphrasing here), “Is the destruction in the flames symbolic of the transformation that comes with a New Year? The fiery brilliance a celebration of the volcanic beauty of the country?” He assured me there was not any special significance and that in Iceland (like many places) they simply liked to make big fires at parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We headed back to the Airbnb. Britney started to pack our stuff-up. I sat on the balcony and watched the fireworks sparkle across the city. At 11PM the fireworks paused as 90% of Icelandic citizens went inside to watch an annual cultural comedy sketch-show. Britney and I pulled-up an English subtitled version of the 2018-2019 episode. We found most of the bits funny and prided ourselves on how &lt;em&gt;earnestly&lt;/em&gt; we felt we were appreciating the local culture&lt;a href=&#34;#fn8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref8&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These fond feelings soon soured though when we realized that, if we’d left 5 minutes earlier, we could have beaten the locals out and made it to a prime location in front of Hallgrimskirkja church&lt;a href=&#34;#fn9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref9&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Instead we got caught in the deluge of people reclaiming their spots and had to settle at the edge of the courtyard, pressed against the buildings. We still had a great view but I was jealous of my parents who had left only minutes before us and were now seated at the &lt;em&gt;exact&lt;/em&gt; location I had picked-out&lt;a href=&#34;#fn10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref10&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fireworks started to pick-up again. Explosions came in different colors from all directions. The show felt layered, distant rockets from disparate launch sites cascaded across the sky. Smoke clouded the landscape and captured the light making each new flash brighter than the one previous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/gD8ObcwygPw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Britney and I went back to the apartment around 12:30AM. Britney went to sleep early&lt;a href=&#34;#fn11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref11&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I stayed up watching the fireworks from our balcony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/u8OiLoBV3uw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dad texted me the bar where he and mom were. He misspelled things terribly but I eventually figured it out and headed down to meet them. Mom didn’t know dad had texted me so was overcome with excitement at the seemingly serendipitous event of me ending up at the same bar as them (an idea I didn’t spoil until the next morning). She’d made friends with a Swedish couple. They exchanged numbers and plans to visit each other in their respective countries&lt;a href=&#34;#fn12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref12&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I drank hot cocoa and Moscow Mules and told stories about my wonderful bride-to-be. The Swedish woman told me tales from her trip. She showed me a picture of her and her husband in front of a beautiful aurora but explained that she actually hadn’t seen it with her naked eyes. Their ‘aurora guides’ had needed to use a high-exposure cameras to pick-up the light&lt;a href=&#34;#fn13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref13&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. She described the whole ‘aurora hunting’ tour as a ploy only good for capturing instagramable photos. I felt proud of the few wispy seconds Britney and I had caught the night before on our drive back from Diamond Beach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My parents thanked me for compelling them to stay up to watch the fireworks for the New Year’s Eve celebrations. They staid out while I went back in. I laid down next to Britney. Fireworks pounded at the windows but I had no trouble sleeping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iceland is famous for their unique flavors of ice cream served year round.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of dishes at the Blue Lagoon had featured this volcanic salt prominently and my parents love fancy salts.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which she ended-up not liking.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I asked several vendors where I might be able to purchase fireworks for myself but was out of luck as they weren’t for sale to tourists in the city at this point. Apparently the fireworks were sold at schools or fire stations in public fundraising events held outside of downtown in the weeks prior – my lack of success in this venture was probably a good thing.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn5&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mom stayed back and took a nap so that she’d have the energy to stay-up for the fireworks.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn6&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Likely in part due to our frigid evening in the car the other night&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn7&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of several that are held all around the city.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn8&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I forget where we found a version of the show with English subtitles.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn9&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;That I’d picked-out during my daytime wanderings.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn10&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I climbed-up a few feet on some iron pipes on the building to give us a better view. This was largely unnecessary as the fireworks exploded overhead, so your height relative to the crowd did not particularly matter.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn11&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;She was fighting off a little bit of a head-cold – likely brought on by the frigid night in the car earlier in the trip.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn12&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mom is the kind of person that makes friends in every room she enters&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn13&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The guides had called them ‘ghost auroras’.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Iceland Day 4: Southeast Coast &amp; Diamond Beach</title>
      <link>/2019/12/30/iceland-day-4-southeast-coast-diamond-beach/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/30/iceland-day-4-southeast-coast-diamond-beach/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Britney and I awoke several times in the night to the frigid cold. We would run across the street to a patch of trees where we could relieve ourselves and get away from the streetlights. I looked up to the stars and the clear night sky clinging faintly to a hope that whatever damage might be done to the car, it was all part of a plan for us to be at this exact point. For what? – maybe to see a brilliant aurora. “What’s an engine compared to a bucket-list experience?” I’d try to convince myself. The stars were beautiful but there were no dancing lights this night to ease my conscience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to fall back asleep I had to put my head completely under the blankets and make my breath into a mini-heater (we didn’t turn the car on out of fear of damaging the engine). This made me claustrophobic and mildly concerned about CO2 poisoning but was better than letting the icy air get my face. I finally got some sleep. (When we eventually got the car working we had to scrape the ice off both the outside as well as the inside of the car.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got-up a little before 9AM and tried calling ‘Mr. Kristy’. It didn’t connect, I had the wrong number. I put my boots on and ran down the street to a rental car company that was just opening. The manager there pointed me to a car repair shop two stores over. At the shop they mentioned a Mr. Kristy – I cheered (Kristy it seemed specialized in fixing this issue for Nissan’s – which he apparently did a dozen times a day in the summer months). They called him, he said he’d be there in ten minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ran back to the car. In 30 minutes, we were fixed-up with no damage to the engine, the correct gas in the car, and a fair fee paid. PRAISE!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We adjusted our plans so that we’d get to Diamond Beach around sunset and then would drive back to Reykjavik at night (and hunt for auroras). On the way to Diamond Beach we stopped at various stunning water falls along the coast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/Li9tx68.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Seljalandsfoss falls&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Seljalandsfoss falls&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6ie3-znWsVM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the top of Skogafoss Falls were thousands of bird nests&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/D__9kYs9Hug&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our 4-hour drive took us over a diversity of landscapes that included rocky deserts, cliff faces with frozen rivers, and multi-mile wide beaches formed from glacial movements. It was a dazzling drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/yYMQUUQ.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;One of dozens of small frozen waterfalls we drove past&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;One of dozens of small frozen waterfalls we drove past&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first black sand beach we stopped at was Reynisfjara. Reynisfjara has a pedestaled cliff face that you can easily climb-up and overlook the crashing waves from the North Atlantic ocean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/MjtnDIn.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/hXXBdMu.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the edge of the ocean are the remains of ancient basalt rock columns. Icelandic legend has it they were formed by trolls dragging a ship towards land who were stopped in their tracks and turned to stone by the dawning sun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/2JQKvoK.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the far side of the beach is a shallow cavern of glistening jagged rocks. A light drip of water was falling from overhead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/x7ZVW3g3snE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the way to Diamond Beach our longest stop was a hike we took up Skaftafell falls. The waterfall inspired the design of the famous Hallgrimskirkja church near our apartment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/jGtK66T.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We finished our hike and raced to Diamond Beach where we caught the last glimmers of daylight. The ‘diamonds’ come from nearby glacial runoff that gets polished in the ocean and then washes up here as tremendous shimmering blocks of ice that blanket the black pebble beach&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/5q2wSlM.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Arriving at Diamond Beach&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Arriving at Diamond Beach&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/VgP05YA.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;On one knee giving Britney this 10,000 carat rock&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;On one knee giving Britney this 10,000 carat rock&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/sKHn2a5.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Submarine shaped ice&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Submarine shaped ice&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/ZDCH5fN.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Dolphin shaped ice&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Dolphin shaped ice&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I laid there for a while. High tide started to come in and the approaching sound of massive ice blocks tumbling in the waves alerted me that it was time to head back. Britney took a nap in the car. I started us back West.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The return trip was more direct, we made just two quick stops. One in the town of Hof to see a church that looked as though it grew from the earth and belonged in The Shire. Another was an unsuccessful search for a geologic site we’d skipped over in our rush to get to Diamond Beach before sundown&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sky was clear now. We drove for long stretches with the windows rolled down peering at the unfiltered stars. Three hours into the drive Britney noticed a faint greenish-gray fluttering. We gasped and shouted excited confirmations to each other of what we were seeing. It was wispier than clouds but moved like liquid in the sky. In just a few seconds it dissolved into the blackness of the night. That ghostly image was the only glimpse of an aurora we caught on the trip. We should have pulled over at that spot as the sky soon filled with clouds and our hunting was over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’d see these same birds and nesting behaviors on the cliffs of the black sand beach at Reynisfjara.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A few miles beyond this spot would have taken us to the opening of Eyjafjallajökull which erupted in 2010 causing havoc in Iceland and Western Europe.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;At local foodtrucks in a campsite down the road we picked-up a lobster roll, lobster bisque (Britney’s third on the trip so far), fried cod and fries, then headed back to Diamond Beach.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;When we stopped to search, we did see a cloistered group of people in minivans that seemed surprised at us stopping near them. At first we thought maybe they were star gazing but it seemed they were meeting for some other purpose we could not divine. We continued on our way.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Iceland Day 3: Thingvellier &amp; Disaster</title>
      <link>/2019/12/29/iceland-day-3-thingvellier-disaster/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/29/iceland-day-3-thingvellier-disaster/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;We slept in a little later this morning (930AM), had Skyr parfaits with mom and dad for breakfast and more croissants from Brauð &amp;amp; Co. We drove back to the UNESCO World heritage site, Thingvellier, that we’d attempted to visit the morning before. We arrived close to sunrise (there was no creepy white pickup truck in the parking lot this time).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The drive out was beautiful and easy. The browning grass and gnarled branches by the road seemed almost a pastoral desert (except for all the wetness). The dim sunlight softened the jagged lines of volcanoes that could now be seen in the distance. The foreign space we had driven through in fear and darkness 26 hours prior now felt almost inviting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thingvellier is important for many reasons, most of which have to do with different kinds of &lt;em&gt;meetings&lt;/em&gt;. It is where the North American and Eurasian plates meet to create stunning crevices and rock formations. It’s where ancient Icelandic village leaders met for inter-tribal gatherings and formed some of the earliest representative(-ish) government structures in Europe. It is where Iceland’s independence was signed after the second World War. Thingvellier’s stunning beauty makes it unsurprising that the site has served as a significant location across much of Iceland’s history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/IMWiLed.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Where American and Eurasian continental plates meet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Where American and Eurasian continental plates meet&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all this significance around me I was floored… several times… &lt;em&gt;literally&lt;/em&gt; – the icy rocks contributed but so did my getting distracted by the stunning views at every step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/IjAMOnS.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Britney had spiked crampons and was sure-footed, I mostly struggled on behind her.&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Britney had spiked crampons and was sure-footed, I mostly struggled on behind her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/QEO1VgY.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/RjHIkAO.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the snow was paved off the main path and pushed into mounds against the rock formations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/Ics51i8.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At higher points the snow piled up to 20 meters over the trail. We took these as an opportunity to go sledding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_D5lehIvB68&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also explored Thingvellier’s many small rivers and lowlands. When the wind settled the water would become as clear as glass. Some places were filled with coins and wishes people had thrown in&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/3yHTaZG.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The drive back after sunset was equally stunning. We met my parents for 530PM reservations at Perlan (“The Pearl”) for dinner. The restaurant was encased in a glass dome and rotated to give a slowly moving &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(360^{\circ}\)&lt;/span&gt; view overlooking the city. It was a nice family dinner, complete with competitions over who could calculate the speed of rotation of the building first&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/BQLf0YW.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Dinner at Perlan&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Dinner at Perlan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After dinner we packed-up for an overnight trip down Iceland’s southeast coast. We planned for a five hour aurora hunt &amp;amp; drive towards black sand Diamond Beach, where we planned to camp for the night in the SUV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside the city, we stopped for gas. Britney was getting extreme cravings for pizza and had the Subway worker do their best to construct a veggie pizza for her&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I was hyper-focused on using the green pump to fill the car with (as the Nissan X-trail was a diesel rather than petrol vehicle).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We resumed our drive and Britney remarked that her dad had almost gotten her a diesel Volkswagen Bug when she was in college but had been nervous about someone borrowing it and filling it with the wrong type of gas. I noted that if you had stickers on the fuel cap and relevant locations in the car (as our rental did) that I thought it would be &lt;em&gt;pretty difficult&lt;/em&gt; to make such a mistake. Britney disagreed and we started to debate the topic. In the middle of me making a snide remark, the car started to hiccup. I slowed down but it kept lurching. We were over an hour from Reykjavik.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I pulled into the gas station of a tiny town and got out to look at the fuel pumps. A sinking feeling ran over me as I noticed that petrol was &lt;em&gt;green&lt;/em&gt; and diesel was black (reverse of the colors in the USA). We called the gas station and had them look up the order associated with my credit card, which confirmed my mistake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent the next hour reading worst-case scenarios on the damage I might have caused the engine&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. We looked-up numbers for the rental car company and emergency car repair, most of which didn’t answer and none of which could help us. A taxi pulled-in behind us. A large pale man in a black fluffy jacket and matching hat stepped out and began filling up his car. I approached him and explained our situation. He called someone on our behalf. A ‘Mr. Kristy’ answered who indicated he could come by in the morning. The cabby gave me the number and I told ‘Mr. Kristy’ I would give him a call if we weren’t able to fix it before then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After struggling through options for another hour we decided to call it quits, get some sleep, and start afresh in the morning. Through all of this Britney was as magnanimous as any person you have ever met.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Though signs discouraged doing such.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Britney and I continued to order seafood. Though for my starter I had goose soup. We should be eating more goose in America. Whatever happened to a Christmas goose? Bring it back!&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite them being out of mini-pizzas, flatbread, mozzarella, and several other key ingredients.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;And feeling more idiotic than I’ve ever felt in my life.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Iceland Day 2: Golden Circle &amp; Snowmobiling</title>
      <link>/2019/12/28/iceland-day-2-golden-circle-snowmobiling/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/28/iceland-day-2-golden-circle-snowmobiling/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;I grabbed an assortment of croissants from Brauð &amp;amp; Co, half a block from our apartment. We were on the road headed East by 7:05AM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The morning was strikingly dark. Clouds obscured any starlight. A soft rain made everything reflective. Faint glimpses of small trees and twisted wooden branches looked like alien figures on the side of the road. I drove nervously, stooping over the wheel like my dad had the morning before. Leaving Reykjavik, I sped through a robotic speedometer that flashed as I passed it – the light surprised me and caused me to drive exceedingly slow for the next hour&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We arrived at the UNESCO World Heritage Site, Thingvellier, at 8:10AM. There was a white pickup truck driving in loops at the far side of the parking lot, otherwise it was empty. I left the keys in the car and stepped out to explore. It was still pitch-black but the rain had stopped and, other than the pickup in the distance, the lot was silent. Britney and I felt as if we were in the beginnings of a horror movie (but did not mention this to one another until later). I walked towards the nearest building. A motion sensor clicked and automated lights flickered on. It was a water closet. I edged towards the next building, the Information Center, which noted that the park didn’t open until 9:00AM. I peered inside at maps and museum placards before wandering around to the side. I turned on my phone’s camera light but it was too dark to pick-up a trail. I looked back and saw the white pickup had parked &lt;em&gt;not quite far enough away&lt;/em&gt; from where Britney sat in our SUV. I hurried back. We buckled-up and continued on our way to Gulfoss Falls, the meeting point for our 10AM Snowmobile-Glacier tour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the drive we saw mysterious orange hazy lights illuminating the clouds. The colors were too static to be auroras; the sky wasn’t clear enough anyways. There also weren’t any cities out this far that could explain them. We went on several detours trying to identify their source. These took us down dirt roads and across small one-lane bridges. Eventually we had to turn back towards Gullfoss Falls without an answer. The off-roading helped my confidence though and for the rest of the trip (across black lava cracked landscapes, icy winds, …) I felt comfortable behind the wheel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We arrived at Gulfoss Falls at 9:30AM&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. We waited in the car with the heat on. Other tourists slowly filled-up the lot around us (I kept an eye-out for the white pick-up but never saw it). Our bus pulled-up; “Mountaineers of Iceland” was printed on the side in lavish maroon letters that reminded you this was a staged attraction. However the tremendous wheels of the vehicle, almost twice the diameter of those on our Nissan X-trail, still made us excited as we imagined the fissures of ice and mud it was designed to take us over. We crowded into the bus carrying a pack of snacks and big smiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sun rose, the ascent up the glacier was our first view of Iceland’s remarkable natural volcanic beauty. Each new mountain seemed larger and icier than the one before. As we traversed Langjokull glacier the temperate rainy climate turned into a foggy snow flurry. We were dropped-off at a large wooden barracks that had several feet of snow piled against it. We ran into the warm interior, changed into jumpsuits, and put on scratched-up motorbike helmets with thick front visors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/pJUIcb4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Our jumpsuits&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Our jumpsuits&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there another truck (with even larger wheels!) picked us up. Fifteen bumpy minutes later we were dropped off in front of rows of snowmobiles and a half dozen guides. We approached a woman in her early 20’s of Southeast Asian descent who wore a white and blue stitched beanie and carried a somewhat aloof though friendly demeanor&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/rUyAWAT.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Britney on our snowmobile&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Britney on our snowmobile&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She showed us the key parts of the snowmobile, the correct distance to follow at, and what to do if we got lost or fell off. Britney and I took the third vehicle in line (behind the guide and an unassuming older-middle aged woman). I drove for the first stretch with Britney behind me. The guide explained that you could either hold onto your partner or onto the bars on the side. She warned that if you held onto your partner you’d both be going down together. Britney chose the bars, which proved to be a good decision&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tour started fast and stayed that way. Visibility was bad and made worse by the thick visor that fogged-up with each breath (which came quicker as we sped along and I became increasingly fatigued). Turning was a sheer act of will that required lurching your bodyweight from one side of the vehicle to the other. This was made more difficult by me frequently losing sight of the path, getting off the main trail, and needing to push through thick patches of snow to get back on track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I strained to keep the dim taillights of the lead snowmobiles in front of me. In the gaps between flurries I’d put my visor-up and squint through the blistering wind, doing my best to keep sight of them. Pride and fear kept us from falling behind. Grace kept us from falling off. The only real breaks came from snowmobilers behind us who tipped over or got left behind and who we had to circle back for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 30 thrilling, grueling, awesome minutes, we got to a rest spot. The guide was pleased and said we were one of the fastest tours she’d had&lt;a href=&#34;#fn5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Britney and I shared a congratulatory kiss before splaying our exhausted selves out in the snow, a sad excuse for snow angels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We drank water, snacked, built a snowman, and got in a half-hearted snowball fight with the tour guides before hopping back on our snowmobile. This time with Britney in front.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/yTgpSWq.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ride back was equally gripping&lt;a href=&#34;#fn6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. We again had a few near falls but made-it. After the tour we chatted with the middle-aged woman who had been immediately in front of us. She was from the Northeast United States and visiting the country with her daughter&lt;a href=&#34;#fn7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref7&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. We learned she was an expert alpine skier (which helped explain why she was such a badass snowmobiler). We changed out of our jumpsuits and took the scenic ride back to our cars&lt;a href=&#34;#fn8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref8&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We walked to an overlook of Gulfoss Falls&lt;a href=&#34;#fn9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref9&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It was so windy and cold we only stayed for a few minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/Y4O832o.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Gulfoss falls&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Gulfoss falls&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next stop was Geyser (the &lt;em&gt;OG&lt;/em&gt; of geysers, as in the &lt;em&gt;original geyser&lt;/em&gt; that all other geysers are named after). Geyser is no longer active, but several other geysers at the site are. Some barely more than gurgle, others, like Strokkur, go off every 8 minutes and can have eruptions as tall as 40 meters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/5VMjtS_U9wU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/wXvQgZ8.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;bubbling geysers&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;bubbling geysers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For dinner, we went across the street to Geyser hotel. I was a bit of a nuisance to get us a table by the window where we could watch eruptions while we ate. At one point two geysers went off back-to-back, making a double geyser&lt;a href=&#34;#fn10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref10&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a relaxed dinner we drove 35 minutes southwest to Secret Lagoon (a small hot springs). It was dark again and the mysterious orange lights returned. We tracked one down and learned they were greenhouses that stayed artificially lit through Iceland’s long nights&lt;a href=&#34;#fn11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref11&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Secret Lagoon was next to a greenhouse and colored the hot spring’s steam in a smokey fire orange&lt;a href=&#34;#fn12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref12&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lagoon is the oldest operating public pool in the nation. It is not fancy (almost the anti-Blue Lagoon) but provided a perfectly subdued end to our day. We grabbed a few floaties&lt;a href=&#34;#fn13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref13&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and spent the next few hours drifting through the hot water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/uMXkC2izpSY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hot springs have their temperatures regulated. However even relatively small ones are so big that it’s impossible to keep the temperature constant. This pool in particular featured patches of cool spots as well as searing hot spots. It became a game to dodge the extreme parts and find the most amenable areas to float in. We took turns with one person laying back on floaties and the other person dragging them on a tour around the pool&lt;a href=&#34;#fn14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref14&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;We eventually realized it was perhaps the only speedometer in the country.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I walked around in the parking lot a little bit – I could hear Gulfoss Falls in the distance, but it was still dark and hard to find my way around.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Almost all Icelandic natives are white, and I wondered if she was visiting from New Zealand or Australia and was working here for the winter (as is common in sky resorts in eastern Washington) but I couldn’t quite place her accent.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Driving the snowmobile proved utterly draining. If she’d held onto me (as I’d encouraged) I’m sure we’d have ended-up in the snow.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn5&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;And that we’d gone 50, 60 kms, when 30’s was more typical.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn6&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Years of jetskiing behind my older brothers in the North Carolina isles had made me attuned to leaning with Britney’s turns.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn7&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Who had been a few vehicles behind us and was one of the individuals that had fallen off.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn8&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which Britney slept through.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn9&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;When we’d arrived in the morning it had been too dark to see the falls, there was just the sound of pounding water in the distance. Being able to now &lt;em&gt;see&lt;/em&gt; it was an absolute delight.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn10&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you like double rainbows, you would love double geysers.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn11&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because of all the geothermal activity in Iceland, energy is VERY cheap, so greenhouses make more economic sense and are the only way to grow fresh produce on the rocky, bracken island&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn12&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;To ‘prepare’ for our float we first pulled into a parking spot that was shaded from the greenhouse lights and took a 40 minute nap.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn13&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which rested by the dozens all around the rim of the pool.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn14&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;By “taking turns” I mean that Britney spent most of the time laying back on the floaties while I pulled her around the springs&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Iceland Day 1: Landing &amp; City Tour</title>
      <link>/2019/12/27/iceland-day-1-landing-city-tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/27/iceland-day-1-landing-city-tour/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;My parents, Britney and I landed in Reykjavik at 630AM. We’d taken an eight-and-a-half-hour overnight flight from Seattle. It was dark when we stepped off the plane and would remain dark until 11AM (in wintertime Iceland only gets 4-6 hours of sunlight a day).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I packed the bags into haphazard piles that poured over the rear storage area of our rented Nissan X-trail. The air was a cold mix of rain and mist. Dad struggled with the defroster and drove with a frenetic nervousness that was magnified by a lack of sleep, food, or familiarity with his surroundings. The first jerky turn launched a carry-on into Britney’s chest. For the remainder of the drive I strained to hold the luggage in place while everyone, except dad and I, caught up on rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was too dark to see the landscape. The first interesting ‘sights’ were the abundant (though not ostentatious) Christmas decorations. We passed a complex of three 15 story apartment buildings where every room facing the highway had a Christmas tree with lights on in the window.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/sEjzjnh.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Picture was taken later but shows the consistency of Christmas decorations in apartment windows&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Picture was taken later but shows the consistency of Christmas decorations in apartment windows&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few missed turns we eventually made it to our apartment building. Britney and my Airbnb had a cute living room and a full (though miniaturized) kitchen. The bedroom was spacious (when there’s scarcity Britney tends to spread out and take over whatever space is nominally mine – be it on the floor, the bathroom counter, the couch, …). We were on the top story. Our ceilings sloped inwards accommodating the building’s roof&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The apartment was formed into a sort of trapezoidagon that forced us to duck at the edges of the rooms – if we weren’t tourists this would have been annoying but for us it added a perfect dash of charm. We had a balcony that faced the North end of the city and the ocean. Stepping outside you could see the spotlight from the Imagine Peace Tower (in honor of John Lennon) shining into the clouds from a nearby island&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Through the south window the top edge of the Hallgrimskirkja church (just a block away) peaked-out over the buildings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My parents’ room was four floors below in the relatively spacious basement. Mom took a nap while dad, Britney, and I wandered the streets for food. It was still early, most places were closed but we eventually stumbled into a boutique hotel’s breakfast buffet. I had 5 carrot-beat shots, 4 cups of Skyr (Icelandic yogurt) parfaits, and an array of fermented cod (some of which I loved, some of which I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; did not) and smoked salmon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Britney and I planned on a 12PM “free” (tip based) walking tour but took a nap that lasted until 12:15PM so ended-up at the 2pm tour. It was still wet outside when we left. The wind and rain at times reminded us of that from our respective hometowns: it could be temperate, polite but almost passive aggressive, like in Seattle; at other times it whipped at your face and made you beg for mercy, as in Chicago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On our walk to the Althingi Parliament House (the tour meeting point) we passed a 20-foot black metal feline structure with piercing red eyes and great yellow teeth. It looked as though it had been born in Hell and sprang from one of Iceland’s many volcanoes. From our guide we learned that it was a sculpture of the ‘Christmas Cat’ who, legend has it, would devour people that didn’t get new clothes for the holidays&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The Christmas Cat also worked as an agent of the giantess Gryla, an Icelandic (and murderous) version of Santa Claus, who snatched bad little children up to a cave and cooked them into a stew. Throughout the trip, whenever I got on Britney’s nerves she’d threaten she was going to call Gryla to come and get me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/KTSCV07.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The Christmas Cat and I&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The Christmas Cat and I&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our guide Arik&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was good humored and welcomed the many questions I peppered him with throughout the tour. He also wore an oversized thick yellow jacket, similar to one I’d brought for the trip, which provided an immediate source of kinship between us&lt;a href=&#34;#fn5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/07U5IhQ.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Rainbow street, in the distance you can see Hallgrimskirkja church&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Rainbow street, in the distance you can see Hallgrimskirkja church&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In back of the parliament building and just in front of Tjornin Lake was a statue of a man in a suit walking with a cube of stone over his head (get it?), named “Monument to the Unknown Bureaucrat”&lt;a href=&#34;#fn6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I asked Arik about politics in Iceland, and if people were frustrated with their leaders in the same way citizens in other (larger) nations tend to be. He explained that with a population of less than 400,000 people&lt;a href=&#34;#fn7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref7&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; they have more direct access to politicians but contended there are still many of the same frustrations and a similarly wide range of ideologies. He also noted a greater concern with nepotism… I argued it was an issue in American politics as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.imgur.com/tm76mFe.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Monument to the Unknown Bureaucrat (i.e. blockhead)&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Monument to the Unknown Bureaucrat (i.e. blockhead)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We ended the tour at the beautiful City Theatre of Reykjavik. As parting gifts Arik gave us chunks of licorice from local vendors and provided some closing notes about the country and its people&lt;a href=&#34;#fn8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref8&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I thought about continuing to chat with Arik and seeing if I might be able to get us invited to a local Icelandic house party&lt;a href=&#34;#fn9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref9&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. However I started to get shy and all I could muster were a few increasingly random questions. I left a good tip and stepped away awkwardly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That evening Britney and I went to an excellent seafood restaurant, Messin. We ordered Arctic salmon and Arctic char. Britney also got lobster soup as a starter (the first of five she would order over the course of the trip!). Everything was fantastic&lt;a href=&#34;#fn10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref10&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;#fn11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref11&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. After dinner we got our day pack ready for the following morning and called it an early night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a suburban American home it might have been an attic&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The monument was erected by Yoko Ono. She chose Iceland because of its clean air. ~80% of the country’s energy comes from water &amp;amp; geothermal energy rather than coal or other sources. Also it’s a country the size of England but a population of only ~360,000, so not too many people to pollute it.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Naturally, the sculpture was located in the main shopping center, doing its best to compel consumerism.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Arik”s difficult to pronounce Icelandic name served as his opening joke to the mostly foreigners in the group.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn5&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This jacket had earned me the nickname ‘big-bird’ from a former roommate – it had come from the way I looked when downhill skiing and my tendency to almost flail my arms when going too fast around a turn or over a mogul.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn6&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which provides a picture of Icelandic wit.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn7&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The relative smallness of the parliament building, and all other national buildings reminds you just how small Iceland is. This made their qualifying for the world-cup and showing-up at the world stage in other competitions that much more impressive to me.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn8&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example that they don’t pass familial names down between successive generations (their last names come directly from their parents first name).&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn9&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Preferably for over New Year’s Eve.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn10&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The salmon even rivaled the fantastic Pacific salmon I grew-up eating in Seattle.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn11&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The portions were also pretty big.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>