<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>programming on Bryan&#39;s website</title>
    <link>/categories/programming/</link>
    <description>Recent content in programming on Bryan&#39;s website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/programming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Using across() to build functions with dplyr, with notes on legacy approaches</title>
      <link>/2020/06/25/using-across-to-build-functions-with-dplyr-with-notes-on-legacy-approaches/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/25/using-across-to-build-functions-with-dplyr-with-notes-on-legacy-approaches/</guid>
      <description>Function expecting one columnFunctions allowing multiple columnsOlder approacheslibrary(tidyverse)dplyr, the foundational tidyverse package, makes a trade-off between being easy to code in interactively while being more difficult to create functions with. The source of the trade-off is in how dplyr evaluates column names (specifically, allowing for unquoted column names as argument inputs). tidy evaluation has been under major development the last couple of years in order to make programming with dplyr easier.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use Flipbooks to Explain Your Code and Thought Process</title>
      <link>/2020/06/24/use-flipbooks-to-explain-your-code-and-thought-process/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/24/use-flipbooks-to-explain-your-code-and-thought-process/</guid>
      <description>Learning R’s %&amp;gt;%Using the pipe operator (%&amp;gt;%) is one of my favorite things about coding in R and the tidyverse. However when it was first shown to me, I couldn’t understand what the #rstats nut describing it was so enthusiastic about. They tried to explain, “It means and then do the next operation.” When that didn’t click for me, they continued (while becoming ever more excited) “It passes the previous steps output into the first argument of the next function,” still… 😐😐😕.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tidy Pairwise Operations</title>
      <link>/2020/06/03/tidy-2-way-column-combinations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/03/tidy-2-way-column-combinations/</guid>
      <description>OverviewI. Nest and pivotII. Expand combinationsIII. Filter redundanciesIV. Map function(s)V. Return to normal dataframeVI. Bind back to dataFunctionalizeExample creating &amp;amp; evaluating featuresWhen is this approach inappropriate?AppendixInteractions example, tidymodelsExpand via joinNested tibblesPivot and then summariseGif for social mediaSession infoOverviewSay you want to map an operation or list of operations across all two-way1 combinations of a set of variables/columns in a dataframe.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>animatrixr &amp; Visualizing Matrix Transformations pt. 2</title>
      <link>/2020/02/24/animatrixr-visualizing-matrix-transformations-pt-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/24/animatrixr-visualizing-matrix-transformations-pt-2/</guid>
      <description>This post is a continuation on my post from last week on Visualizing Matrix Transformations with gganimate. Both posts are largely inspired by Grant Sanderson’s beautiful video series The Essence of Linear Algebra and wanting to continue messing around with Thomas Lin Peterson’s fantastic gganimate package in R.
As with the last post, I’ll describe trying to (very loosely) recreate a small part of the visualizations showing the geometry of matrix multiplication and changing basis vectors (using gganimate in R).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>