<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>probability on Bryan Shalloway&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/probability/</link>
    <description>Recent content in probability on Bryan Shalloway&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/probability/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Gambling Where the House Almost Always Loses... but Still Wins</title>
      <link>/2020/10/28/idea-for-casino-games-where-the-player-almost-always-win/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/10/28/idea-for-casino-games-where-the-player-almost-always-win/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In this post, I will describe an example of a game that produces many small wins for the player and occasional large wins for the house. Such a game (theoretically) takes advantage of psychological biases of individuals to prefer gains to be disaggregated and losses to be aggregated as well as a general disposition for accepting small sure-things when it comes to gains and a willingness to chance higher-risk scenarios in order to avoid paying losses.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All ideas described in this post are theoretical and would need to be tested in a gambling / gaming environment. The ideas described are very much in a draft form&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday’s I co-lead an internal study group on Pricing Strategy. We just finished week four of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/learn/uva-darden-bcg-pricing-strategy-customer-value/home/week/4&#34;&gt;Customer Value in Pricing Strategy&lt;/a&gt;. The material in this section is devoted almost entirely to the various conditions under which people behave ‘irrationally’&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and how / when a firm can manipulate the psychology of customers to demand a higher price for their products. The subject matter is rife with ethical dilemmas; setting these aside, the material sparked an idea for a new spin on games and gambling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few psychological phenomena from the course that are important primers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I. People tend to be &lt;em&gt;risk seeking&lt;/em&gt; when facing &lt;strong&gt;losses&lt;/strong&gt; but &lt;em&gt;risk averse&lt;/em&gt; when facing &lt;strong&gt;gains&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example in the course is that, faced with the scenario below, people will tend to go for the sure thing and win $50 rather than the chance at gaining $100 (even though each option has the same expected value).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2020-10-29-idea-for-casino-games-where-the-player-almost-always-win_files/gain-example.PNG&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;(all images in this post are screenshotted from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/learn/uva-darden-bcg-pricing-strategy-customer-value/home/week/4&#34;&gt;coursera materials&lt;/a&gt; created by the University of Virginia and Boston Consulting Group)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However when facing potential losses, people prefer taking their chances and will tend to select the option with the risk of a greater loss (for the possibility of avoiding the loss entirely). They will choose a 50% chance of losing $100 (to avoid a guaranteed loss of $50).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2020-10-29-idea-for-casino-games-where-the-player-almost-always-win_files/loss-example.PNG&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: upper-roman&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People tend to prefer &lt;em&gt;disaggregated&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;gains&lt;/strong&gt; but &lt;em&gt;aggregated&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;losses&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People prefer multiple small good events over a single (larger) good event (even if the total value is equal). For example, people will prefer winning two low value scratch cards over winning a single higher value scratch card:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2020-10-29-idea-for-casino-games-where-the-player-almost-always-win_files/aggregated-gains.PNG&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However people prefer taking losses in aggregated forms. As described in the course, they usually prefer receiving one large bill over multiple smaller bills:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2020-10-29-idea-for-casino-games-where-the-player-almost-always-win_files/aggregated-loss.PNG&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though, as with the previous examples, the value of the events are equal&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;implications-for-gambling&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Implications for Gambling&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many lotteries, slots, and other forms of gambling run counter to these particular psychological phenomena&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. They offer repeated guaranteed initial losses (the quarter you put into the machine, the scratch ticket you buy from the counter, etc.) for the chance at a large payoff (winning the jackpot).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought an interesting set-up for a game would be one that flipped this and made the player very likely to win a small amount each time they played but that always carried the risk of a single large loss&lt;a href=&#34;#fn5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example, imagine a roulette-like wheel numbered from 1 to 10. You are instructed to pick a number. As long as you &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; land on that number you will win $5. If you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; land on it you will lose $50 (or something along those lines for whatever size of bet&lt;a href=&#34;#fn6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). This particular bet would yield the casino an expected value of 50 cents&lt;a href=&#34;#fn7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref7&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It also yields the player the excitement of an expected nine wins in a row&lt;a href=&#34;#fn8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref8&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The advert for the game might focus on the idea of “Tempting Fate&lt;a href=&#34;#fn9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref9&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could blend these ideas with other common gaming features. For example, you might have a mix of ‘big losses’ and ‘big wins’. Carrying on from the previous example, the wheel (numbered 1:10) could be set-up where the player selects a number for a ‘big win’ ($50 gain), and two ‘big losers’ ($50 loss for either), and the rest resulting in small wins ($5). The expected value for the casino on this set-up is now $1.50.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a variety of forms this game could be tested in – it doesn’t have to be a roulette-like wheel in a casino (I actually think an app or more gamefied environment may work better&lt;a href=&#34;#fn10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref10&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;em&gt;The novel feature is ensuring players get repeated high-likelihood small wins while having them pay their losses in one-off large losses (rather than small incremental payments).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is a decent chance I misapplied some concepts – particularly regarding the idea of risk seeking when it comes to losses (e.g. if it’s more about seeking uncertainty vs seeking riskiness…). What I describe also seems to run counter to the idea that sporadic positive events help drive repeat behaviors whereas sporadic negative shocks drive avoidance of the activity. Generally I would need to think about and read a little more…&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am also in the middle of reading Khaneman’s highly related seminal book “Thinking Fast and Slow”.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ignore the particularities in the examples and focus on what they are designed to illustrate…&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;However they play at others. Casinos are master psychological manipulators. I imagine they have thoroughly tested the ideas discussed in this post.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn5&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Picture a group of friends playing credit card roulette at the end of the night.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn6&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;one can of course edit the odds to set things appropriately&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn7&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I imagine casinos have considered setting games like this up and that there are good reasons they don’t exist. For example, players have to put up a lot of money to win anything, so the dollars that go to the house per dollar bet is going to be much lower than other games that they could fill their floor space with.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn8&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;https://math.stackexchange.com/questions/1119872/on-average-how-many-times-must-i-roll-a-dice-until-i-get-a-6#:~:text=About%2014%20times%20it%20will,100%20and%20get%20%E2%89%886.&#34;&gt;thread&lt;/a&gt; for explanation.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn9&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many casino games could be redesigned in this manner – where you are likely to win but always face the risk of a large loss. You might picture a room in the casino that had an ‘Upside Down’ style feel where all the slots and similar games there were reconstructed accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.thesun.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/tmp_6e95hn_8581834aa802f9b6_wv_publicity_post_launch_still_10-0000011.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn10&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an example imagine a facsimile of a game where you search fantastical caves for treasure – you usually find small bits, but occasionally stumble upon a pack of dwarves that rob you. If the game points are translatable into money this represents the same thing. An app environment also helps to divorce the user from the sting of the extreme losses (that come from the design of this type of game).&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>