<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>visualization on Bryan&#39;s website</title>
    <link>/categories/visualization/</link>
    <description>Recent content in visualization on Bryan&#39;s website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/visualization/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Riddler Solutions: Pedestrian Puzzles</title>
      <link>/2020/03/04/riddler-solutions-pedestrian-puzzles/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/03/04/riddler-solutions-pedestrian-puzzles/</guid>
      <description>Riddler expressRiddler classicAppendixTime to centerTransform city, prettyThis post contains solutions to FiveThirtyEight’s two riddles released 2020-02-14, Riddler Express and Riddler Classic. I used animatrixr (a toy package I wrote) to help with some of the visualizations and computations for this post. For more details on animating matrix transformations see my posts here and here.
Riddler expressThe riddle:
Riddler City is a large circular metropolis, with countless square city blocks that each have a side length of 1 km.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>animatrixr &amp; Visualizing Matrix Transformations pt. 2</title>
      <link>/2020/02/24/animatrixr-visualizing-matrix-transformations-pt-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/24/animatrixr-visualizing-matrix-transformations-pt-2/</guid>
      <description>This post is a continuation on my post from last week on Visualizing Matrix Transformations with gganimate. Both posts are largely inspired by Grant Sanderson’s beautiful video series The Essence of Linear Algebra and wanting to continue messing around with Thomas Lin Peterson’s fantastic gganimate package in R.
As with the last post, I’ll describe trying to (very loosely) recreate a small part of the visualizations showing the geometry of matrix multiplication and changing basis vectors (using gganimate in R).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing Matrix Transformations with gganimate</title>
      <link>/2020/02/20/visualizing-matrix-transformations-with-gganimate/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/20/visualizing-matrix-transformations-with-gganimate/</guid>
      <description>I highly recommend the fantastic video series Essence of Linear Algebra by Grant Sanderson. In this post I’ll walk through how you can use gganimate and the tidyverse to (very loosely) recreate some of the visualizations shown in that series. Specifically those on matrix transformations and changing the basis vectors1.

This post is an offshoot of an (upcoming) post of my solutions to this week’s FiveThirtyEight Riddler. To support my solution, I was trying to visualize matrix transformations.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>